The Guide to the Pittsburg, Shawmut & Northern Railroad Company papers, 1872-1960
Pittsburg Shawmut Northern Railroad Company, 1872-1960
- Loose-leaf notebooks, A count of all the photographs and material other than actual text in these volumes follows. THESE PHOTOGRAPHS AND OTHER MATERIAL MUST BE COUNTED EACH TIME ANY OF THESE VOLUMES IS REMOVED FROM THE STACKS AND RECOUNTED BEFORE THEY ARE RETURNED TO THE STACKS (see note signed by
  - Book No. 3, frontispiece (preceding P. 255) - map of P.S. RR. and connections
    - p. 93 Letter dated Jan. 14, 1946 from J. Taney Willcox (secretary, Pennsylvania RR.) to C.F.H. Allen re extent of Rochester, N.Y. & Pa. RR. owned lines. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 94 Letter dated May 7, 1947 from F. H. Wells to C.F.H. Allen re disposition of records of P.S. & N. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 95 Letter dated May 20, 1947 from Thomas C. Buchanan to C.F.H. Allen re possibility of obtaining railroad records that would otherwise be destroyed. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 96 Letter dated June 2, 1947 from J. N. Thompson (General Manager) to C.F.H. Allen-cover letter for items sent (map, corporate history & Timetables) (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 97 Letter dated June 5, 1947 from F. M. Opel (General Auditor) to C.F.H. Allen re request for certain railroad records. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 98 Chart showing development of P.S. & N. from parent and subsidiary companies (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 99 (no. 8 at top of page) Notes re Soranson's comments on early mining attempts in Pa. by railroads (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 100 Titled "Notes from Mr. Lathrop, call of 2-19-49 " re people connected with P.S. &N. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 101 Letter dated Feb. 13, 1949 from Fred C. Hill to Allen re pictures of old locomotives (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 102 Letter dated Jan. 18, 1949 from R. J. Finch (Chief Mechanical Engineer, American Locomotive Co.) to Allen re information and photographs of old locomotives (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 103 Letter dated Feb. 1, 1949 Finch to Allen - similar to letter of Jan. 18. (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 104 Letter Dated Feb. 4, 1949 Finch to Allen - similar to previous two letters (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 105 Letter dated Feb. 11, 1949 from Gerald M. Best (vice-president, Ry. & Locomotive Hist. Soc.) to Allen in answer to questions about locomotives built at the Cooke Works (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 106 Letter dated April 12, 1949 from J. D. Dickinson (M'gr. Locomotive Sales, Lima-Hamilton Corp.) to Allen re locomotives built by the company for the Buffalo, St. Marys & Southwestern line (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 107 Letter dated Mar. 4, 1949 from Luria Bros. & Co. to Allen in answer to query on final disposition of certain locomotives (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 108 & 109 Letter dated Feb. 8, 1952 from Interstate Commerce Commission to Allen re locomotive numbers and disposition of these (P.S.&N. locomotives) (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 110 - 112 Letter dated April 23, 1950 from Roscoe Davis to Allen providing information about the Marvin Creek operations (lumbering) (Box 1, Volume 3)
    - p. 113 Chart - titled "Engineering Dept. Blueprint" dated Oct. 24, 1909, This is a copy (made with blue ink on ordinary white paper showing the names, mileage of various predecessors, and subsidiary lines to the P.S.&N. and also indicating dates of construction and mergers. [This page is loose-not punched and on rings]. (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Miscellaneous Envelopes, This box contains material that is separated as to subject matter. The material is, for the most part, in manila envelopes. Each envelope bears a legend as to its contents. The following list includes the legend on each envelope and a physical inventory of the contents.
    - 1. Shay Locomotives (Railroads in Western N.Y. & Pa. for Goodyear roads - B. & S. component parts - Kaul & Hall, St. Mary's, Pa.), 12 Mss. pcs.; 9 photographs (Box 2)
    - 2. Letters from S. R. Wood (mostly on pertinent engines), 1950-1957, 46 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 3. Map P.S.&N. (Large, accurate), 2 maps. (Box 2)
    - 4. Shawmut notes of C.F.H. Allen (correspondence on C. N.Y.&W. locomotive #43. Probably it was the repair engine "Danbury"), 1950., 2 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 5. Loose note re Jones, pres. of Buffalo, N.Y.&Pa. etc.), 1 Mss. pc. (Box 2)
    - 6. W.N.Y.&Pa. (old engines [photos] - several negatives B&S.-Erie [maps]), 1951., 1 Mss. pc., 12 photographs. (Box 2)
    - 7. Photo of Prattsburgh Ry. No. 2 (ex-Buffalo, Rochester & Pittsburg No. 126), 1 photo. (Box 2)
    - 8. Loose-letter dated Nov. 30, 1951 to Allen from S.R. Wood (and list of engines) re engines built by Brooks Locomotive Works., 2 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 9. Original copy (and 2 copies) of news clippings on P.S.&N. from Mr. Lathrop's books., 60 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 10. Derailment Reports, Boiler Inspections, Records showing lines and ownership (valuable for tracing back) 1908-1914., 193 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 11. Miscellaneous Shawmut (1899, narrow gauge receipts; 1900 local T.T.; 1919 about boilers of 2 locomotives 11 and 18 and one narrow gauge; 1908 "paper"; Nugent's bridge list [published]; 1903 T.T., 15 Mss. pcs.; 1 pamphlet (timetable) (Box 2)
    - 12. Shawmut 8 × 10 enlargements:, 19 photos (Box 2)
    - 13. C.N.Y.&W. timetable, April 24, 1899, #17, 3 Mss. pcs. (photostats) (Box 2)
    - 14. Shawmut Stock Certificates (correspondence 1953, photostats and stock certificates). 30 Mss. pcs. (includes 9 photostats of certificates and 12 original certificates). (Box 2)
    - 15. Evidence that there was a No. 2 (not on the Clarion River) 7 Mss. pcs. (all photostats - duplicates of p. 195 in notebook). (Box 2)
    - 16. Clarion River (photos of engines & map (4 copies) of line, 16 photos. (Box 2)
    - 17. P.S.&N. original of circular on Stony Brook Bridge. 6 Mss. pcs. (Circular 1907; 4 sheets of specifications for Lord & Lady Baltimore engines; B. & O. loaded car certification card - blank). (Box 2)
    - 18. Latest used notes - last P.S.&N. typing - R.Wy & P. and early parts, 89 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 19. P.S.&N. "paper" misc. notes from junk. 46 Mss. pcs. (includes 2 Blueprints of bridge masonry foundations). (Box 2)
    - 20. P.S.&N. rolling stock pages sent to S.R. Wood - Parts omitted from P.S.&N. bulletins 92, 93, 96 -- largely personal items which should have been used. 115 Mss. pcs. (included 2 photostats of sections of line). (Box 2)
    - 21. Part 3 P.S.&N. (published) correspondence on locomotives included (1955-1956)., 17 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 22. 2 maps (includes 3 blank pass request forms, Pittsburgh Press, June 1, 1947 article on P.&S. attempt to attract industry along line, maps of P.S.&N. and Lehigh and New England routes)., 2 maps; 3 Mss. pcs.; 1 newspaper clipping. (Box 2)
    - 23. Loose material (seniority roster of enginemen of P.S.&N. and three typescript memos, 2 copies of descriptive pamphlet welcoming visitors of Nat. Ry. Hist. Soc. May 30, 1954 P.&S. RR.; 15 page typescript of minutes of 20th executive staff meeting, Jan. 29, 1908 P.S.&N.)., 19 Mss. pcs.; 2 pamphlets (Box 2)
    - 24. C.N.Y.&W. "paper" (historically valuable), 1899-1923., 5 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 25. A lot of Chapman letters, L. & S.W. 1889-1890 (vice-president Lackawanna & Southwestern RR.)., 38 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 26. Allegany Central "paper" - L. & S.W. train orders from file of F.S. Hammond., 5 Mss. pcs. 1885 and 1890. (Box 2)
    - 27. L. & P. paper 1886-8 (valuable, especially the payroll draft). 3 Mss. pcs. (payroll draft dated Oct. 15, 1886 on Chatham National Bank of N.Y. pay to order of Dan'l. McCartey $11.63). (Box 2)
    - 28. Soranson's letters - mostly Shawmut (but he mixes subjects, so some may be B.&S., etc.). Some about people living and could not be published with other parts of P.S.&N. articles (e.g. - John B. Dickson, et al.) 1942-1948. 54 Mss. pcs. (attached to letter, Oct. 19, 1942, between pp. 2 & 3, is a playing card, the joker, sent to Allen because of the lithograph on the back. The card is not counted as part of the 54 pcs.) (Box 2)
    - 29. "to give away [?]" - Boiler inspection, etc. 1909-1935., 33 mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 30. P.S.&N. original picture - new shipment of engines arrives at Angelica from Mott's (probably only one extant)., 1 photo. (Box 2)
    - 31. Inspections, Stationary Boiler #5889 (or #1-3) Shay gear #693 (#11, 14, 18, old locomotives) 1913&1917., 14 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 32. P.S.&N. Corporate History - Old timetables - Blueprint of P.S.&N. (very large - folded). 1 Mss. vol. (typescript of corporate history, blueprint bound in with this, as of the date of valuation June 30, 1919 - Office of Auditor May 31, 1923 ). (Box 2)
    - 1 pamphlet (P.S.&N. timetable #2, Nov. 15, 1903 - this has been folded as it is rather large. The edges are torn in several places and it is in generally fragile condition.) (Box 2)
    - 33. P.S.&N. - extra copy of roster - I.C.C. 3 pp, of 2nd copy - C.N.Y.&W. earlydrafts., 39 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 34. Used notes - L.&P., L.&S.W., C.N.Y.&W., P.S.&N., R.N.Y. & P., 90 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 36. P.S.&N. mostly enlargements - one original and rare print., 67 photos (not all identified) (Box 2)
    - 37. Nile Wreck - extra pictures from Mott's negatives., 16 photos. (Box 2)
    - 38. Allegany County Advocate, Jan. 9, 1902, Angelica, N.Y., 1 newspaper - single issue. (Box 2)
    - 39. Simpsons' Daily Leader, August 22, 1913, Kittanning, Pa. (story on first train run on Pittsburg & Shawmut line). 1 newspaper - single issue [in very poor condition]. (Box 2)
    - 40. R.R. maps - Allegany Cty. L.&S.W. -- N.Y. State 1894, 1900 - P.S.&N. 1900, photo copies. 23 photos (includes maps, timetables and correspondence). (Box 2)
    - 41. Bullis letters - McKean County and Western N.Y. railroads 1948-1957., 9 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 42. Mostly about the Kanes Mt. Jewett K.&R. RR. (Kushequa Line); also Kane & Elk RR. (Elk City, McKean County), 1909-1950., 72 Mss. pcs.; 14 photos. (Box 2)
    - 43. Nugent's letters - mostly Shawmut, 1948-1952., 122 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 44. P.S.&N. - list of negatives of C.F.H. Allen and Mott collections -- class numbers of Shawmut locomotives., 7 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 45. Clarion River, 1905, 1947-1951., 28 Mss. pcs. (Box 2)
    - 46. P.S.&N. - older locomotives (2. L. 1. P.&S.)., 5 photos. (Box 2)
    - 47. Buffalo & Susquehanna (Wellsville & Buffalo?), Soranson's letters, etc., 1943-1947., 29 Mss. pcs.; 1 T.C., 12 photos, 17 maps. (Box 2)
    - 48. A few of P.S.&N. negatives from C.F.H. Allen's collection (there are copies of timetables, stock certificates, maps, passes)., 13 photos. (Box 2)
    - 50. 2 maps of N.Y. RR's. 1894 and 1900., 4 photos. (Box 2)
    - 51. P.S.&N. "Janelyn" business car and subsequently in use in Mexico., 7 photos. (Box 2)
    - 52. Erie Narrow Gauge System - also Pennsy narrow gauge system and miscellaneous small roads, Penna. RR. maps, 1930-1950., 42 Mss. pcs., 24 photos, 16 maps, 1 newspaper clipping. (Box 2)
  - Box #3
    - 35. Shawmut correspondence (all sources) 1942-1960., 161 Mss. pcs. (Box 3)
    - 1. Envelope marked "Shawmut Real Estate" (Box 3)
      - -- charts indicating physical description of road (# of bridges, lengths, etc.) and other information (such as annual labor outlay, etc.), 19 Mss. pcs. (Box 3)
      - - 1920-1947, Lease of Edward B. Simmons, Angelica, N.Y. - for pasture lands., 20 Mss. pcs., 5 maps (Box 3)
      - - abstracts of title for land owned by Linus Graham and apparently sold for railroad right-of-way, Allegany County, N.Y., 1893, 1901, 32 Mss. pcs. (Box 3)
      - - photostatic copies of pp. 166, 167, 168, 169, 170, 173 of a (unknown) deed book, indenture conveying lands of - the Rochester, Nunda & Penna. RR. Co. to the Allegany Central RR. Co. by sale forced by foreclosure of mortgage (p. 173 is a sketch showing the stretch of track near Swain, N.Y., part of which was a horseshoe curve), 1881., 85 Mss. pcs. (Box 3)
      - - deed conveying lands held in trust by Frank Sullivan Smith to the Shawmut Holding Corporation (executed by Clara A.H.H. Smith, executrix of F.S. Smith estate)., 38 Mss. pcs. (Box 3)
    - 2. 4 Mss. pcs. - agreement between P.S.&N. and Belvidere Block Corp. for construction and maintenance of spur track (p. 1 of agreement is missing). (Box 3)
    - 3. Envelope marked "copy of P.S.&N. map, with connecting lines inked in by C.F.H. Allen., 4 photos. (Box 3)
    - 4. Envelope marked #35 mm. negatives" (Box 3)
      - Old RR's. N.Y. Comm. map 1884 (Box 3)
      - Nile Wreck map by Nugent (Box 3)
      - Mt. J.K.&R. timetables 1912 (Box 3)
      - P.S.&N. 1902 map and timetables (Box 3)
      - Stony Brook Glen new bridge (Box 3)
      - Sketch maps - Clarion River RR, Mt. J. & S. RR. (Box 3)
      - P.S.&N. flyer "loop de loop" 1903 timetable (Box 3)
      - C.N.Y.&W. inspections (Box 3)
      - Lathrops P.S.&N. clippings, 24 pp. (Box 3)
      - Copies L.&S.W. timetable - L.&S.W. letter of George Chapman (Box 3)
      - One strip unidentified (Box 3)
    - 5. Envelope marked all P.S.&N. from J. W. Brauner 33 photos, 1 Mss. pc. (Aug. 17, 1952 cover letter for photos) (Box 3)
    - 6. Blueprint of Main Line of B.&S. - Sagamore to VanHusen only. (Box 3)
      - Track chart, Alignment & Profile 1 map (rolled as it is very long) (Box 3)
    - 7. Loose-leaf cover filled with photographs, 45 photos (Shawmut shops and engines) (Box 3)
    - 8. 3 × 5 file cards, arranged alphabetically, -- information consists of name of individual, to which road or line he was connected and position or positions held., Approximately 400 cards. (Box 3)
    - 9. Two iron spikes from (Box 3)
      - a. Kane & Elk RR., James City, Pa. abondoned Jan. 1946 (Box 3)
      - b. Clarion River RR., Pa. abandoned 1948 (Box 3)